Filip Nikšić

Phone: +1 215 454-9531 Email: fniksic@gmail.com Web: https://fniksic.github.io

Research Interests Broadly, I am interested in the analysis, verification, and testing of concurrent

and distributed systems. My doctoral research focused on applying combinatorial techniques to systematic and random testing of distributed systems. More recently, I have been working on programming models and testing techniques

for distributed stream processing.

Education

09/2012–05/2019 Max Planck Institute for Software Systems

Doctor of Engineering (Dr.-Ing.) degree by Technische Universität Kaiserslautern

Dissertation: Combinatorial Constructions for Effective Testing

Grade: summa cum laude

10/2009–10/2011 Department of Mathematics, University of Zagreb

Enrolled in a doctoral program in mathematics

07/2004–10/2009 Department of Mathematics, University of Zagreb

Dipl. Ing. (4-year degree) in Mathematics (profile: Computer Science)

GPA: 4.7 / 5.0

Work Experience

09/2020–present Google, New York City, NY

Software engineer

10/2018–07/2020 University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA

Postdoctoral researcher, working with Rajeev Alur

09/2012–10/2018 Max Planck Institute for Software Systems, Kaiserslautern, Germany

Doctoral researcher, advised by Rupak Majumdar

05/2016–08/2016 Microsoft, Redmond, WA

Research intern working on a testing and fault-injection framework for concurrent

software. Technologies: C#, .NET Compiler Platform ("Roslyn")

04/2010-09/2012 IN2 d.o.o., Zagreb, Croatia

Software engineer developing financial software. Technologies: Oracle DB (SQL,

PL/SQL), Java (Spring Framework), and Adobe Flex

Teaching Experience

01/2019–05/2019 University of Pennsylvania

Occasional lectures and a student project for CIS 540: Principles of Embedded

Computation (Spring 2019)

10/2016–02/2017 Max Planck Institute for Software Systems (MPI-SWS)

Teaching assistant: Program Analysis (Winter 2016/2017)

04/2014–07/2014 Max Planck Institute for Software Systems (MPI-SWS)

Teaching assistant: Verification of Reactive Systems (Summer 2014)

03/2008–09/2009 Department of Mathematics, University of Zagreb

Student assistant: Set Theory (Summer 2008), Introduction to Parallel Comput-

ing (Winter 2008), Application of Parallel Computers (Summer 2009).

09/2002-06/2005 Informatics Club NET, Ivanić-Grad

Tutored high school students for programming competitions

Professional Service Artifact evaluation committee: ISSTA 2015, ECOOP 2018, CAV 2019

Conference reviews: CAV 2013, CSL 2013, FMCAD 2013, EMSOFT 2014, FMCAD 2014, LICS 2014, CADE 2015, VMCAI 2015, POPL 2016, TACAS 2016, VMCAI

2017, ICALP 2018

Journal reviews: ACM Transactions on Computational Logic, Acta Informatica

Technical Skills

Operating systems: GNU/Linux, Mac OS X, Windows

Programming languages: C/C++, C#, Java, Python, PL/SQL, ActionScript (Flex)

Databases: Oracle DB

Language Skills Croatian (native), English (fluent), German (basic)

Publications

Konstantinos Kallas, Filip Niksic, Caleb Stanford, Rajeev Alur. *DiffStream: Differential Output Testing for Stream Processing Programs.* PACMPL 4 (OOPSLA) 2020

Cezara Drăgoi, Constantin Enea, Burcu Kulahcioglu Ozkan, Rupak Majumdar, Filip Niksic. *Testing Consensus Implementations Using Communication Closure*. PACMPL 4 (OOPSLA) 2020

Filip Niksic. *Combinatorial Constructions for Effective Testing*. Doctoral dissertation. Technische Universität Kaiserslautern, May 2019.

Burcu Kulahcioglu Ozkan, Rupak Majumdar, Filip Niksic. *Checking Linearizability Using Hitting Families*. PPoPP 2019

Burcu Kulahcioglu Ozkan, Rupak Majumdar, Filip Niksic, Mitra Tabaei Befrouei, Georg Weissenbacher. *Randomized Testing of Distributed Systems with Probabilistic Guarantees*. PACMPL 2 (OOPSLA) 2018

Recipient of OOPSLA 2018 Distinguished Paper Award

Rupak Majumdar, Filip Niksic. Why is Random Testing Effective for Partition Tolerance Bugs? PACMPL 2 (POPL) 2018

Dmitry Chistikov, Rupak Majumdar, Filip Niksic Hitting Families of Schedules for Asynchronous Programs. CAV 2016

Ivan Gavran, Filip Niksic, Aditya Kanade, Rupak Majumdar, Viktor Vafeiadis. Rely/Guarantee Reasoning for Asynchronous Programs. CONCUR 2015

Sumit Gulwani, Mikaël Mayer, Filip Niksic, Ruzica Piskac. *StriSynth: Synthesis for Live Programming.* ICSE 2015

Javier Esparza, Ruslán Ledesma-Garza, Rupak Majumdar, Philipp Meyer, Filip Niksic. *An SMT-Based Approach to Coverability Analysis*. CAV 2014

Johannes Kloos, Rupak Majumdar, Filip Niksic, Ruzica Piskac. *Incremental, Inductive Coverability.* CAV 2013